Finding Aid for Lawrence B. Lindemer papers, 1954-1977 and 1981-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lawrence B. Lindemer papers 1954-1977, 1981-1982, 1964-1976 and 1981-1982
Lindemer, Lawrence B. 1921-
3 linear feet
851683 Aa 2
Chairman of the Michigan Republican Party, Regent of the University of Michigan, Michigan Supreme Court justice. Political files include activities as Republican State Chairman and his involvement in the presidential campaign of Nelson Rockefeller (1964) and George Romney (1967-1968); also files from his service as regent of the University of Michigan (1969-1975) and justice of the Michigan Supreme Court (1975-1977).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Lawrence B. Lindemer (donor no. 3956 ). The bulk of the collection came to the library in 1993.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Lawrence B. Lindemer was born in Syracuse, New York on 21 August 1921. He completed two years at Hamilton College in Clinton, New York, then transferred to the University of Michigan where he received his B.A. in 1943. In 1940, during his college years, he married the former Rebecca Mead Gale. The Lindemers had two sons: Lawrence, Jr. and David G.
Upon graduation from college, Lindemer enlisted in the United States Air Force and served for sixteen months. Sometime in 1944 Lindemer was sent to Officers Candidate School in Miami Beach. Upon graduating he served as a lieutenant for seventeen months. After service in the air force Lindemer attended law school at the University of Michigan, receiving a Bachelor of Law degree in 1948.
In the fall of 1947 Lindemer and his family moved to the village of Stockbridge, Ingham County, Michigan. A community leader, Lindemer served as the chairman of the local boy scout committee, area chairman for the Republican Party of Ingham County, and the area chairman for the United Community Chest Fund Drive. He also participated in the Stockbridge Lion's Club, Stockbridge F.& A.M., and the American Legion.
Beginning in 1951, Lindemer became increasingly active in politics. He was elected to the Michigan State House of Representatives. After serving one term, he was appointed to the Hoover Commission serving consecutive posts as Assistant to Commissioner Homer Ferguson (1953 to 1954), Commissioner Styles Bridges (1955), and was made special assistant to former President Herbert Hoover in 1955.
After his work with the Hoover Commission Lindemer's interests turned back to the Midwest. From 1957 to 1961, he served as chairman of the Michigan Republican party. In 1964, Nelson Rockefeller appointed Lindemer to the chairmanship of the Midwest Region for Rockefeller's unsuccessful bid for the presidency. In 1966 Lindemer ran unsuccessfully against incumbent Frank J. Kelley for the office of Michigan Attorney General. In 1968, Lindemer re-entered politics, serving as the regional chair for George Romney's unsuccessful campaign for president. During this year (1968), Romney also appointed Lindemer to serve as a regent of the University of Michigan. Although he was defeated for election in 1968, he was reappointed in April 1969 to fill yet another vacancy. He then continued to serve as regent until his resignation in 1975.
Concurrent with the development of his political career, Lindemer gained legal experience in both public and private practice. Lindemer's first legal experience was obtained while serving as the assistant prosecuting attorney for Ingham County, (1949-1950). Later, he became a partner in the law firm of Foster, Lindemer, Swift and Collins. Lindemer worked for this firm from 1955 to 1975. Lindemer was also an active member of the State Bar Association of Michigan, the American Bar Association, and the Federal Bar Association. Lindemer became commissioner of the State Bar in 1963. Starting in 1963 Lindemer also served as co-chair of the State Bar Committee on Judicial Selections and Qualifications.
He retained this post on the Judicial Selection and Qualifications Committee until 1975. At this time Governor William Milliken appointed him to the Michigan Supreme Court in 1975 to fill a vacancy created by a justice's death. Lindemer's 1976 campaign to retain this post failed. Milliken also appointed Lindemer to two other posts. He was a special investigator for the inquiry about Lieutenant Governor James Damman's alleged misuse of power and office (1974) and co-chaired the Special Committee on Prison Disturbances after the riots of 1981.
The Lawrence Lindemer Papers contain correspondence, memoranda, official reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, and an audio tape documenting the political and legal career of Lawrence B. Lindemer. While the entire collection spans from 1954 to 1982, the bulk of the records date from 1964 to 1976 with an additional cluster of records dated 1981-1982.
The collection has been divided into four series: Political files; Regent of the University of Michigan; Legal Career, including Michigan Supreme Court; and Other materials. The Lindemer files are especially valuable for their documentation of Lindemer's activities within the Republican Party, as state chairman, as chair of the Midwest Nelson Rockefeller campaign for President in 1964, and his involvement in the presidential candidacy of George Romney for President in 1968.
Subjects:
Damman, James.; Elections--Michigan--1966.; Elections--Michigan--1976.; Judges--Michigan.; Lawyers--Michigan.; Lindemer, Lawrence B.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Michigan. Special Committee on Prison Disturbances.; Presidents--United States--Election--1964.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; Prison riots--Michigan--1981.; Republican Party (Mich.); Republican Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Lindemer, Lawrence B.; Political conventions.; Republican Party (Mich.); University of Michigan. Board of Regents.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Political files
  - Republican State Chairman 1957-1961
    - Decision to seek position 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and other papers
      - January-February 1957 (Box 1)
      - March-April 1957 (Box 1)
      - May-December 1957 (Box 1)
      - 1958-1961 (Box 1)
    - Speeches 1957-1960 (Box 1)
    - Schedules and meetings (Box 1)
    - Analysis of 1960, 1961 elections (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller Campaign 1964
    (Lindemer was the Midwest States Campaign Chair)
    - Central Operations (Box 1)
    - Governor William Scranton candidacy (Box 1)
    - Illinois (Box 1)
    - Indiana (Box 1)
    - Iowa (Box 1)
    - Kansas (Box 1)
    - Michigan (Box 1)
    - Minnesota (Box 1)
    - Nebraska (Box 1)
    - North Dakota (Box 1)
    - Ohio (Box 1)
    - South Dakota (Box 1)
    - Wisconsin (Box 1)
    - Regional Directors Material (Box 1)
    - Republican National Convention (Box 1)
  - Campaign for Office of Michigan Attorney General 1966
    - General (Box 1)
    - Broadcast advertising (Box 1)
    - re. Frank J. Kelley, Incumbent Attorney General (Box 1)
  - Romney Presidential Campaign 1967-1968
    - General 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (mainly campaign memoranda and correspondence)
    - Colorado (Box 2)
    - Indiana (Box 2)
    - Iowa (Box 2)
    - Kansas (Box 2)
    - North Dakota (Box 2)
    - Wisconsin (Box 2)
    - Post-Campaign Material 1968 (Box 2)
- Regent of the University of Michigan 1968-1975
  - Correspondence 1968 (Box 2)
  - Campaign for Office 1968, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1969 (Box 2)
  - Black Action Movement 1970
    - Student Demands (Box 2)
    - Public Reaction to Demands (Box 2)
  - Committee on a Permanent University Judiciary 1970 (Box 2)
  - Book Store Proposal 1969 (Box 2)
  - ROTC Program 1969 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Campaign for Office 1972 (Box 2)
  - Personal and Official Correspondence 1973 (Box 2)
  - Audio-tape of WCBN radio interview March 19, 1970, 1 7 inches audiotape reel-to-reel (Box 2)
- Legal Career, including Michigan Supreme Court
  - Hoover Commission 1954-1956
    - Correspondence and clippings (Box 2)
  - State Bar Committee on Judicial Selection and Qualification Committee
    - Correspondence 1970-1975 (sampled), 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Standing Committee Minutes 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - Investigation of Lieutenant Governor James Damman 1974
    - Cover Letter for Documentary Evidence (Box 2)
    - Final Report (minus exhibits) (Box 2)
    - Notes, Clippings and Memos (Box 2)
  - Michigan Supreme Court Justice
    - Congratulatory correspondence 1975 (Box 2)
    - Case Notes 1975 (Box 2)
    - Case Notes 1976 (Box 2)
    - Case Notes undated (Box 2)
    - Daily Work, Court cases
      - June-October 1975 (Box 3)
      - November 1975-March 1976 (Box 3)
      - May-September 1976 (Box 3)
      - October-December 1976 (Box 3)
    - Daily Work, Correspondence
      - June-October 1975 (Box 3)
      - November 1975-March 1976 (Box 3)
      - April-September 1976 (Box 3)
      - October-December 1976 (Box 3)
    - "Intoxication as a Defense" Memo 1976 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings During Tenure 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings on Appointment 1975 (Box 3)
    - Opinions Written by Lindemer 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - SADO Investigation (State Appellant Defense Office) 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - State Bar Resolution 1975 (Box 3)
  - Gianota versus Milliken, et. al. (Lindemer)
    - Correspondence 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Defendant Materials 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1975 (Box 3)
    - Plaintiff Materials 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Campaign for Michigan Supreme Court Justice 1976
    - Agenda of coming events (samples) 1976 (Box 3)
    - Appeal for assistance 1976 (Box 3)
    - Campaign committee correspondence 1976 (Box 3)
    - Campaign materials 1976 (Box 3)
    - Campaign plan 1976 (Box 3)
    - Contract and agreements 1976 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - January-April 1976 (Box 3)
      - June-July 1976 (Box 3)
      - August 1976 (Box 3)
      - September 1976 (Box 3)
      - October 1976 (Box 3)
      - November-December 1976 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with Baily, Deardourff & Eyre 1976 (Box 3)
    - Detailed Nomination and Election Expenses (also receipts) 1976 (Box 3)
    - Hardin-Schuyler Dinner (fundraiser) 1976 (Box 3)
    - Income and expense reports 1976 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1976 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1976, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Nomination Speech for Lindemer 1976 (Box 3)
    - Press releases and information 1976 (Box 3)
    - Workers 1976 (Box 3)
  - Prison Disturbance Committee 1981
    - Committee Minutes Organization Information (Box 3)
    - Corrections Update 1982 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Committee Members (Photographs), 1981 (Box 3)
    - Initial Official Reports about Disturbances 1981 (Box 3)
    - Interim Reports 1981 (Box 3)
    - Letters from corrections officers 1981 (Box 3)
    - Letters from inmates 1981 (Box 3)
    - Letters from families and friends 1981 (Box 3)
    - Letters from taxpayers (Box 3)
    - Newspapers clippings and releases 1981 (Box 3)
    - Original complaint report from Marquette 1981 (Box 3)
    - Report to Milliken 1981 (Box 3)
    - Response of Corrections Department 1981 (Box 3)
- Other materials
  - Autobiographical sketch (Box 3)
  - Speeches
    - Dated Transcripts and Notes 1975-1977 (Box 3)
    - Undated Transcripts and Notecards (Box 3)
    - circa 1970s (Box 3)
  - China Trip 1976 (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)